<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certain briefe observations and antiquæries: on Master Prin's Twelve questions about church-government. Wherein is modestly showne, how un-usefull and frivolous they are, how bitter and unchristian in censuring that way; whereas there are no reasons brought to contradict it. By a well-willer to the truth, and Master Prin.</title>
            <author>Goodwin, John, 1594?-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91875</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1667</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E10_33</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18171</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860361</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860361</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112481</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91875)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112481)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 2:E10[33])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certain briefe observations and antiquæries: on Master Prin's Twelve questions about church-government. Wherein is modestly showne, how un-usefull and frivolous they are, how bitter and unchristian in censuring that way; whereas there are no reasons brought to contradict it. By a well-willer to the truth, and Master Prin.</title>
                  <author>Goodwin, John, 1594?-1665.</author>
                  <author>Robinson, Henry, 1605?-1664?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare 1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to John Goodwin; cf. BLC. Also attributed to Henry Robinson; cf. DNB and Halkett &amp; Laing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Octob: 4th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prynne, William, 1600-1669. --  Twelve considerable serious questions touching church government.</term>
               <term>Church polity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:112481:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:112481:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Certain briefe OBSERVATIONS AND <hi>ANTIQ<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AERIES:</hi> ON MASTER PRIN's TWELVE QUESTIONS ABOUT CHURCH-GOVERNMENT. Wherein is modeſtly ſhowne, how un-uſefull and frivolous they are; How bitter and unchriſtian in cenſuring that way; whereas there are no Reaſons brought to contradict it.</p>
            <p>By a well-willer to the Truth, and Maſter PRIN.</p>
            <p>Printed in the yeare 1644.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:112481:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:112481:2"/>
            <head>Certain briefe Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations and Antiquaeries on M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> PRIN's Twelve Queſtions about Church-government.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is no ſight ſo lovely, and taking to the eyes of all ingeniuous and ſincere hearts, as naked truth; theſe which know its excellency will ſtudy to find it out. Truth is a jewell which lyes out of ſight, as it were, in the bowels of many reaſons, men muſt ſearch for it, that wil find it out, among truthes, this of Church Government is not the leaſt. There are many things this age hath brought forth about it to little purpoſe; moſt men beating about the buſh; few that I have ſcene have diſcovered it in its nature. Some write ſo voluminous, heaping up ſo many diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions about it, that they rather darken the truth then ſet it forth, rather intangle a mans underſtanding then informe it; others write ſo full of paſſion, as if they writ with poyſon of Aſpes, rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning up mens perſonall failings to diſgrace the Cauſe, not urging their arguments to convince the judgement, (among theſe I have obſerved one Maſter <hi>Edwards</hi> hath the quickeſt pen, and I have often thought that book ſhould rather have been writ by Doct. <hi>Pocklinton,</hi> Doct. <hi>Heylin,</hi> or one of the Archbiſhops Chaplaines, then Maſter <hi>Edwards,</hi> who hath been ſometimes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted godly.) Maſter <hi>Prin</hi> hath begun another way as unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory as any; though we hope there is more candor in his ſpirit: He profeſſeth in the beginning he hath not leaſure to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate the controverſie; and then its wondred why he propounds theſe <hi>Quaeries.</hi> For either, firſt he layes them downe as poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons undiſputable, undeniable in reſpect of the clearneſſe of them
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:112481:3"/>
unto all underſtandings, or becauſe of his name to them; for elſe he knowes (as all know) that have any light in this Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, that all theſe grounds, theſe whom he calls independents will deny, and their anſwer would be negative to every one. Or ſecondly, he propounds them as affirmatives which he intends to prove and cleere by ſolide arguments, and then he muſt have leaſure to do it; and as yet the others negation is as ſtrong as his affirmation, for here is no proofe for it. Or elſe thirdly, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations in which he deſires ſatisfaction as one being in doubt which way to walke, only theſe things for the preſent move him to be of a contrary judgement; the ſtyle of the booke doth not much favour this laſt, as being too full of confidence, and bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: If Maſter <hi>Prin</hi> had ſuch a ſenſe of the publike diviſions, he would not have gone to make the breach wider by ſetting forth <hi>Quaeries</hi> ſtuft with ſuch invectives. I had thought ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings had learn'd Maſter <hi>Prin</hi> a little more meekneſſe; M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Prin</hi> knowes his name is famous abroad, and that the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple will all thinke that that muſt needs be true which he pleads for. Beſides, hee knowes that the Reverend Aſſembly is now controverting of the thing, and that <hi>Quaeries</hi> will do little good while Arguments are expected on both ſides: but ſince they are out let us ſee what are in them.</p>
            <p>The ſumme of the firſt <hi>Quaerie,</hi> is, whether Chriſt hath ſet down in the Word any preſcript forme of government for King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Churches to follow; or whether (ſeeing there be dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent formes of civill government in almoſt every Kingdome) there is not a latitude, and liberty left them by Chriſt to chuſe a government ſutable to their State.</p>
            <p>If this were granted, what abſurdities would follow? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label>
            </p>
            <p>For the Goſpell would be ſtraiter then the Law, Chriſt more unfaithfull then <hi>Moſes,</hi> God ſet a <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 25. 40. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 8. 5.</note> patterne to <hi>Moſes,</hi> which he charged him not to vary fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in a title, that was but a carnal Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in compariſon of this, nay, it was a type of the Church under the Goſpſll, Chriſt ſhould neither be faithfull as a husband, head, nor King of his Church, if he ſhould give others power to order it, to ſuit it as they pleaſed to their owne civill government, not ſetting down his own Lawes for them to walk by. In <hi>Revel.</hi> 11. 1, 2. you reade of a meaſuring of the Temple: Now how can
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:112481:3"/>
you meaſure without a rule? The meaning of that, according to Maſter <hi>Prin,</hi> muſt be thus (meaſured) that is, frame it according to your civill State, a miſerable meaſure for a Church. In <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velat.</hi> 20. 1, its ſaid the patterne of the new <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> (which is but the Church in her pureſt ſtate, the ſame for forme with the former Church) came down from heaven.</p>
            <p>Beſides, look in this <hi>Quaerie</hi> and you ſhall find a contradiction, for he askes whether Church government may not be framed to any civill State if it be conſonant to the Word, and yet queſtions whether there be any rule in the Word.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if no preſcript forme in the Word, why not Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy as well as Presbytery? why ſuch crying down of Biſhops as Antichriſtian, for how can that be more Antichriſtian then any other, ſeeing there is no certain government in the Word? Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy regulated and moderated (if all were knowne) is more conſonant and agreeable to a Monarchicall government then Presbytery.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I aske of Maſter <hi>Prin,</hi> if Church government muſt be ſuited to States, whether Politicians are not more fit to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult about ſtabliſhing it: And why is an Aſſembly of Divines called to ſearch the Word about it? Surely Stateſmen know bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter how to fit the Common-wealth then Divines: there muſt be ſomething in it, ſurely, or elſe the Parliament did very ill to have a Synod. If the Doctrine be true, throw aſide the Bible, in this matter ſtudy the Law; and then it is well done of Maſter <hi>Prin</hi> to write of it, being his profeſſion.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Whether Maſter <hi>Prin</hi> thinks it more reaſon that the State ſhould be ſubject to Chriſts rule, or Chriſt to their directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; that the government of his Church ſhould be fitted to States, or they to it. I know his religion, though his reaſon ſhould ſtand a farre off, would abhor the thought of it: if you, and the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians go on that principle, the Saints will hardly be of your judgement, for they think Chriſt is King alone over his Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and hath not left them to ſubſtitutes, and the politick con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations of men for to governe them.</p>
            <p>Theſe two places you urge out of 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 40. and the 11. 34. where the Apoſtle ſpeehes of doing <hi>all things decently,</hi> &amp;c. is far from this, it being about things that are meerly circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:112481:4"/>
and ordering of things in a Church already conſtituted, not of the conſtitution of any Church.</p>
            <p>The ſecond <hi>Quarie,</hi> in ſumme, is, whether if any govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be ſtabliſhed by any State upon ſerious debate, every one is not bound in conſcience to ſubmit to it, and no wayes to ſeeke an exemption from it, under paine of being guilty of arrogancy, &amp;c. The Scriptures in the margent I wonder to what end Maſter <hi>Prin</hi> quotes them ſo little to purpoſe, looke on that place 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 32. <hi>The ſpirit of the Prophets are ſubject to the Prophets;</hi> how full to the thing let all judge who know the ſcope of that place; by the Prophets there doth he mean the civill State, or the Synod, or both? And is not that ſpoken to a particular congregation, for the regulating the exerciſe of propheſying; or doth he meane by being ſubject, that the Prophets have an authoritative power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the other Prophets; I know not what he means by that place. The other places, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 1, 2. of <hi>ſubmitting to every ordinance,</hi> &amp;c. If that be true, then every man is bound to put out his owne eyes, to yeeld to blind obedience, never to ſearch into the truth, for if he ſearch and find it contrary to the Word, he muſt follow his judgement, and to follow his judgement is to be a Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, to be guilty of arrogancy, &amp;c. to contradict the Word, to oppoſe an ordinance of God; ſo that a man muſt inevitably ſin, take either part. Is not this to uphold the Papiſt tenent of belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving as the Church beleeveth? &amp;c. I put it to Maſter <hi>Prin,</hi> if the Parliament and Synod ſhould ſet up an Epiſcopall government, which he thinkes is Antichriſtian, whether he would not ſpeak a word againſt it? Is not this a baſe bondage, <hi>jurare in verba al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terius,</hi> to give up a mans faith and conſcience to mens direction; but if the former be true, then this ſecond muſt follow, if no rule, then you muſt obey what is commanded you. Suppoſe that is commanded may prove untrue, what if that way be not right, if that Synod and State ſhould erre, what would you thinke of it then? &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I humbly demand of Maſter <hi>Prin</hi> whether he and the other two holy men were not juſtly ſtigmatiſed and cenſured for ſpeaking againſt the Biſhops and Ceremonies? &amp;c. which were ſtabliſhed by ſo many Synods, and Acts of Parliament; and how h<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> can excuſe himſelfe from pride and arrogancy in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:112481:4"/>
ſuch a courſe; for by his owne rule he ſhould have actually obeyed and not ſpake a word to the contrary. Such divinity will over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw all the power of Scripture over mens conſciences, only make that to bind which a Synod thinks good.</p>
            <p>The third <hi>Quaerie</hi> contradicts the firſt, in the firſt hee askes <note place="margin">In this <hi>Quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> hee quotes a ſaying in a Booke called <hi>The bloudy Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent,</hi> which was written by one as contrary to this as the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependents, as he is to the Presbyterians and they ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly diſavow the Booke.</note> whether there be any rule in the Word; here he askes whether that government which hath ſufficient, if not moſt warrant in the new Teſtament is not to be choſen. In this he cryes up the one government (which he inſtanceth in the fourth <hi>Quaerie</hi> to be presbyteriall) as tending to eſtabliſh Chriſtian unity; peace, &amp;c. that which ſerves moſt effectually to prevent Hereſies, Schiſmes, &amp;c. Here is a bare affirmation, and the independents, No, is as good as your, I. Its deſired Maſter <hi>Prin</hi> would prove what hee ſayes, that independent government hath not ſuch expreſſe war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant from the Word (another contradiction) as presbyteriall; prove that, and you ſhall be <hi>Magnus Apollo;</hi> as for the Scriptures you bring will little help you.</p>
            <p>For the fifth, its anſwered by way of conceſſion, that it will overthrow all nationall Churches, as not conceiving any ſuch warrant in the Word, but for any forme of civill government it will ſtand better with them then Presbytery can; the miſchiefes of Presbytery, are vailed with Orthodoxneſſe, and preventing Schiſmes, &amp;c, But if the Saints would pry into the formality, tyranny, inſlaving mens judgements and conſciences the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteriall way, &amp;c. they would looke upon it as that which is moſt inconſiſtent with their ſpirituall liberty, and with State priviledges. Its politickly done of you to put the beſt termes on your owne way how will you have it take elſe; I will let paſſe your bitter expreſſions (that one man would be, if poſſible, a independent Church, and republicke ſubject to no lawes) I thought ſuch language would not ſuit with you ſpirrit, Maſter <hi>Prin</hi> eſpecially that you would not ſpeake ſo of them who were your beſt frinds in your ſufferings; which ſtood to you, and refreſhed you when moſt of your presbiterians (Epiſcopall enough then) were ſhye of you, I could name the men that uſed you kindly whom you now implicitly reproach; the indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents giue more to civell power then your preſbyterians doe; I would faine know whether your presbyterians doe not hold;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:112481:5"/>
that an Act of a Synod or a Nationall Aſſembly is as valid and binding in Eccleſiaſticks, as an Act of Parliament in civills; and whether the Parliament can <hi>de jure</hi> contradict their proceedings, whether they will affirme that the Parliament hath any juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction over them in ſettling Eccleſiaſticall matters, this is not a <hi>Quaerie</hi> without ground; for as far as the independents under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand of the presbyteriall government in Scotland, its abſolutely independent from the Parliament in reſpect of decreeing and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acting matters of government; only this honor presbyterians give to their Magiſtrate, they muſt be the executioners of their Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to hang whom they condemne.</p>
            <p>The ſumme of the ſixth <hi>Quaerie,</hi> is, whether ſince the firſt prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Goſpell, beleevers multiplying, they did not gather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Churches which had dependencie on, and was ſubordinate to Nationall Synods, &amp;c. And if not to ſhow the place where, and to name any eminent Author that ever maintained the contrary. This <hi>Quaerie</hi> is very bold and daring, yet I anſwer that beleevers did as ſoone as they were converted gather into particular Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, as is apparent, but that they were ſubordinate unto Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Synods, &amp;c. <hi>ſub judice lis eſt;</hi> And if in many Kingdomes it might be ſo, <hi>de facto,</hi> yet whether <hi>de jure,</hi> and from a patterne in the Word that we deſire may be proved.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe this ſhould be true, that there cannot in any Kingdom ſuch a Church be ſhowne for many yeares; or at leaſt no Writer expreſſeth it; if ſo be it can be made forth from the Word, and conſonant to the Saints practiſe in the Apoſtles times. I know no ſuch Schiſme in diſſenting from all mens practiſes to follow the cleare truth. You challenge all to ſhow you one eminent Writer who maintained the ſame; I will not go ſo far back into antiquity, as to bring you out a catalogue of Fathers, who though they had not a cleare light in that way, yet had many ſhrowd hints and notions in many things, which are practiſed by theſe you call independent. There be many latter Writers as eminent in holineſſe, and without diſparagement in learning to many whom you can produce for the other: (as learned Doct. <hi>Ames</hi> in <hi>Medul. theolog. de eccleſ.</hi> Maſter <hi>Ainſ<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Maſter <hi>Cotton,</hi> with many of this age knowne unto you, to whom you will not deny eminency in learning) which have ſtood for this way; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:112481:5"/>
doth Maſter <hi>Prin</hi> think we have no more light diſcovered in theſe dayes about Church-government, then the godly had in former dayes; or muſt all the Saints be regulated by former pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes, then ſhould Epiſcopacie be more followed then Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, it being as anciently practiſed, &amp; as learnedly writ for as it.</p>
            <p>Your ſeventh <hi>Quaerie</hi> is the ſame in forme with the firſt and ſixth, and as little in it as in any; for firſt he askes whether the Law of Nature that teacheth men to ſubj<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct themſelves to one publike forme of government in a State, doth not teach to ſubject to a National or Provincial Synod in matters of Church-govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. This is anſwered in the firſt, beſide the independents think that its as ſutable to the law of nature, rectified reaſon, &amp;c. for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry particular man to have his vote in that which moſt concernes him; not to give away his reaſon to another, not to ſubject his conſcience to any but Chriſt; reaſon, and politicks will ſhow, Maſter <hi>Prin,</hi> that there is a ſutableneſſe to the Law of Nature in a <hi>Democraticall,</hi> and <hi>Aristocraticall</hi> government (for this way of Church-government is made up of both theſe) as in Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chicall, or meere <hi>Ariſtocraticall;</hi> beſides, Chriſt hath given to men no ſuch power over mens conſciences, as he hath to Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates over mens bodies. To let paſſe your bitter ſpeeches, ſaying that there is no example for particular Congregations, (which you can Independents) except derived from the conventicles of the Arrians, Donatiſts, and other Heretickes. Leave off theſe names of Heretickes, Maſter <hi>Prin,</hi> you have been paid enough with that title, you may bleſſe God for theſe conventicles, in which you were remembred with teares, when others durſt not name you.</p>
            <p>Maſter <hi>Prins</hi> eaghth and ninth <hi>Quaeries</hi> are in ſumme all one, thus, whether the conceſſion of one Catholike Church, the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall aſſembly of the Iſraelites, the Synodall aſſembly of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles be not an infallible proofe of National Churches of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Presbytery, &amp;c. Its anſwered negatively. And though he ſay that the Independents anſwers are but evaſions, wee ſhall judge them ſolide arguments till we ſee the contrary. The Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall Church of the Jewes cannot be a patterne for us now, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the covenant of the Goſpell is not made with any one par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Nation, as with the Jewes, but to all perſons that em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:112481:6"/>
the Goſpell, and beleeve in Chriſt. You have no promiſe nor propheſie of any Nation to bee holy to God but the Jewes Nation, when they ſhall be called againe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Neither can Maſter <hi>Prin</hi> ſhow any Nation, every member whereof is qualified for to make up a Church; which is the body of Chriſt, unleſſe Maſter <hi>Prin</hi> will take in all drunkards, whore-maſters, &amp;c. to be members of a Church; whereas the Word ſayes, they muſt be viſible Saints; and this cannot be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 1. <hi>Phil.</hi> 5. 1.</note> in a Nationall Church. Neither is that Aſſembly in Acts 15. which you call a Synod, any proofe for a Presbyteriall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. For firſt, I demand whether that Church had not power within it ſelfe to debate the buſineſſe, and ſettle the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, ſeeing there was a great ſtrife among them about it. Secondly, I demand of Maſter <hi>Prin,</hi> whether <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas</hi> had not power (being Apoſtles) to determine the matter, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 15. 1.</note> as well as the Synod of Elders?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Whether they went not up principally to prove the falſe Apoſtles, that werr among them, lyers, for they told them they were ſent by the Apoſtles to make known that they muſt be <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 24.</note> Circumciſed. Now to give teſtimony unto this, that they came not from the Apoſtles, they ſend choſen men to Jeruſalem a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it?</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Whether this was not an occaſionall meeting, not a Synod, which is a collection of the Elders of divers Churches in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a body, but onely ſome of the Church choſen out and ſent to the other Church at Jeruſalem for adviſe.</p>
            <p>Maſter <hi>Prin</hi> may think as ſlightly of the arguments given by the Independents, (as he calls them) from this head, yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his word, hee muſt give them leave to judge they are ſufficient, unleſſe the authority of Maſter <hi>Prin's</hi> name be ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument; the Scriptures quoted ſerve to fill up the margent, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, unleſſe you open them, and argue from them; for theſe texts are uſed by the contrary ſide againſt you, and as validly ſtill as yours, before more be ſhowne.</p>
            <p>The ninth <hi>Quaerie,</hi> Whether the Independents challenging the Presbyterians to ſhow a National Church in Chriſts time, be not an irrationall and unjuſt demand, Anſ. no, if the Scripture hath a forme of government for the Churches of Chriſt in after ages
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:112481:6"/>
to walke in; but to you it may ſeeme irrationall, who thinke Church-government muſt be ordered according to civill State, and be caſt into that mould.</p>
            <p>Maſter <hi>Prin</hi> from his <hi>Quaeries</hi> fals to his Logick, and demands whether a Syllogiſme framed from the former, <hi>viz</hi> No Nationall Church in the Apoſtles time. <hi>Ergo,</hi> None ought to be now, be not as abſurd as theſe.</p>
            <p>There was no meeting of Chriſtians in publike Churches, but in caves, corners, &amp;c. Therefore they ought not to meet in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Churches now, but in caves, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I thought that Maſter <hi>Prin's</hi> Logick would have diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed between the forme of a thing, and the circumſtance of place in the exerciſe of it, which is left to every Churches diſcretion, would this be a good argument in his Logick? that becauſe the ordering of circumſtances of time and place are in the Churches power; therefore the making of new formes of government, is, when the congregation men argue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the not being of a national conſtitution of a Church in the Apoſtles dayes, to the denying of any now; they argue on this ground, being able to make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, that the forme of the conſtitution of Churches in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles time, is a patterne for all Churches to follow, and in no kind to vary from it.</p>
            <p>Againe, he demands whether that way of arguing be not as abſurd as this?</p>
            <p>There was no Nation, Kingdome, City, Republike, Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, Congregationall, or Parochiall Church in <hi>Adam's</hi> younger dayes, before people were multiplied, but a family government.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ergo,</hi> There ought to be none but a Family government now, no man would be ſo void of reaſon, no truly Sir, neither did the Independents think you would be ſo void of reaſon, as to father ſuch an abſurdity on them, who are as rationall as your ſelfe.</p>
            <p>As for Civill government, let men alter it as they will, and if God will alter the government of the Church, as he did from a Family into a Nation among the Jewes, and if againe from a Nation God will alter it unto a oeconimicall or congregationall, we muſt yeeld.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Againe, whether it be not as abſurd as this: Every man in his infancy is born deſtitute of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, reaſon, &amp;c.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:112481:7"/>
Therefore he ought to continue ſo when growne a man.</p>
            <p>The Chriſtian Church in the Apoſtles time, while in her infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie was not National, but ſo and ſo, (what I pray) (not Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. How know you that, Maſter <hi>Prin,</hi> we will not take your word.) <hi>Ergo,</hi> It ought not to be Nationall now. Here obſerve Reader.</p>
            <p>Maſter <hi>Prin</hi> accounts the Church in the Apoſtles time, a poor weak Church, that had not ſo much reaſon for things then, as we have now; the Apoſtles, the ſtabliſhers of it, weake men; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as there was more light of the Goſpell, and gifts of the Holy Ghoſt powred out then, then ever ſince; even private Chriſtians being as able to deale in the things of God, as moſt of our Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and Miniſters are now; yet Maſter <hi>Prin</hi> compares the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing that patterne, the following of a child in his infancy, that hath neither reaſon nor religion. Maſter <hi>Prin,</hi> follow you your perfect Church, wee will follow this infant patterne, and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, is not this argument you bring to faſten an abſurdity on them, as abſurd as this.</p>
            <p>The Scriptures were writ in the infancy of the Church, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wiſer and better Scriptures may be writ now, the Church being growne up into a Nation, having ſo many reverent Divines in it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, You would needs make a Nationall Church State more perfect, underſtanding, and ripe Church then a Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall; we would thinke ſo too, if we had a Word for it.</p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay the Hiſtory of the Acts ſhowes that as beleevers multiplied their Church goverment and diſcipline va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, its anſwered if you meane by varying, that things before eſtabliſhed by the Apoſtles in any Church was altered, its denied, and pray ſhow the place if you meane by varied that they added rules for goverment as occaſion ſerved we grant it, for as they received not the knowledge of the Goſpell at once ſo neither of diſcipline, neither had the Churches need of all the rules at once, but as God fitted occaſions ſo he made knowne rules, yet ſo as at length to diſcover the whole forme of his Houſe, as he did the whole myſtery of divinity, to be as rule to all generations after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you ſee what your logicke is come to Maſter <hi>Prin,</hi> draw better conſequences next.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:112481:7"/>
Your tenth <hi>Quaerie</hi> is the ſame in ſumme with your ſecord, only there you ſpeake in generall, here you perticulariſe, and you aske of the independents whether in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience they are not bound to ſubmit unto presbyteriall goverment in caſe that the Parliament and Synod ſhould eſtabliſh it; and whether it would not be a high degree of ob<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>nancy ſingularity, ſelfe end, &amp;c. to oppoſe this forme of government.</p>
            <p>I Anſ. If you require this of them, &amp; charge them ſo highly in not ſubmiting, I hope you will ſhow your authoritie; either you would have them ſubmit becauſe what they comand is of divine inſtitution, or becauſe commanded by their authority, if in the former ſence, they muſt haue eyes to ſee it as well as the Synod, or elſe their obedience will be hypocriticall moſt diſpleaſing to God; if in the latter, then the Popes councel, decreeing any thing muſt out of as much conſcience be obeyed by theſe that be under his authority, as the beſt things commnded by a Godly Synod, for <hi>a quatenus ad omne valet conſequentia;</hi> if becauſe they command, then what ever they command muſt be done; I put the caſe to M. <hi>Prin,</hi> whether when he challenged all the Divines in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land to make good againſt them that Epiſcopacy was not <hi>jure de vino,</hi> whether if the King had called a Synod and had concluded it as the moſt Divines thought; he would have given up his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to their votes and ſubmited to their determination, it had beene hight of arrogancy, ſelfe ends, ſchiſme in Maſter <hi>Prin</hi> not to do ſo, &amp; ſo in point of law when moſt of the Judges had given in their judgements contrary to M. <hi>Prin,</hi> why did not hee ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, becauſe the contrary was cleere to him, and he had ſinned a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainſt his own conſcience if he had gone back one jot from his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion; what if independency ſhould be ſet up, what if the Synod ſhould maintaine the errours of Antinomians, &amp;c. was Maſter <hi>Prin</hi> bound in conſcience to ſay as they did, to ſpeake againſt it would be ſhiſme, faction, arrogancy, &amp;c, Maſter <hi>Prin</hi> how is your ſpirit changed what wil you now ſubmit to any thing, are you become a time ſerver? have you given up your faith to other men? when Synods can ſay as they, Acts 15. it ſeemeth good to the Holy Ghoſt and us to lay theſe things on you, then wee will thinke we are bound in conſcience to ſubmit, elſe you muſt helpe us with new eyes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:112481:8"/>
In your eleventh <hi>Quaerie</hi> you go on in your way of bitterneſſe and aske whether that independencie be not a wombe to all ſchiſmes, hereſies, &amp;c. its Anſwered no, its a ſeminary of holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe a nouriſher of love, a way to build up unto the fulneſſe of Chriſt, your presbyterial way is a way inflauing mens co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences; cruſhing the parts of theſe Saints which you <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>all Lay-men, is a way to depreſſe truth to hinder growth in grace and Spirituall communion with Chriſt, the Saints ſhall ſoone find it ſo.</p>
            <p>In the laſt <hi>Quaerie</hi> M. <hi>Prin</hi> falls a jeering of his brethren. He would needs father a child on them, of the presbyterians beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; they have put a nickname on them to make them odious, and now he asketh whether it be not an inſolent proud name, &amp;c. unfit for any Chriſtian to arrogat, your presbytereans have pretty ſlights to defame theſe that are of a contrary opinion; as if one ſhould call an honeſt man theefe, and aske a man whether it were not a ſhamefull thing for him to be given to ſtealing. Know Maſter <hi>Prin</hi> theſe men ſcorn the name, they have diſavowed it in <note n="*" place="margin">See M. <hi>Simp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed.</note> print; the terme is more fit for you &amp; theſe whom you ſtand for, a terme fit for your provinciall, and nationall Synods from whom there is no appeale, but to whoſe judg ments all muſt ſubmit as to an ordinance of Chriſt, &amp; though but to queſtion what is done by them is to be guilty of faction, ſchiſme, arrogancy; theſe you call independants, confeſſe that they are accountable for their actions to every neighbour Church that ſhall in the name of Chriſt require it, they ſtand not independent from others but hold communion with all other Churches, both in the ordinances, and asking counſall and adviſe mutually; to let your other looſe lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage paſſe much with what is in the former; take ſome Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an adviſe; remember you have not your hand in darkening the glory of any of the Saints; take heed of defaming a way w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> for ought you know may be a way of Chriſt; it will coſt you many a ſigh afterward if God ſhould convince you, you know Chriſt will never owne bitterneſſe in maintaining any way though conſonant to his Word. Remember, neither you nor the Synod are infalliable, but as ſubject to errors as others; never more dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Hereſies confirmed then by Synods (I ſpeak not this to caſt <note place="margin">Concil. Trent.</note> any blot on Synods or this Synod eſpcially in which there are many holy and learned men) but to ſhow that a man is not bound
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:112481:8"/>
in conſcience to follow their decrees upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> penalty of ſin, arrogan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, &amp;c. and not to ſeeke the leaſt exemption from what they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin whoſe decrees may be ſubject to as great errors as any. Oh that a ſpirit of love were maintained among theſe which are bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, though men differ in judgment muſt they needs differ in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection! M. <hi>Prin</hi> if you will needs be buſie in this controuerſie leave off your <hi>Quaeries</hi> for we will deny them all; ſtate your que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion; ſet forth your arguments, open the Scriptures you quote to fill up the margent, be as breefe as may be; call in your paſſion and conſider, and doubt not of an anſwer to what you ſhall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtly ſet forth.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
